Within a block of code for catching errors, you
may want some code to run no matter the outcome
of the try portion of the code. The except block
executes when an error occurs, preventing a crash.
Else runs if there are no exceptions to code,
meaning no errors were caught by the except
block. The finally block is a code block that runs
whether the try portion of a code block worked or
did not. I have the code example from the previous
topic open in a new file version, the 524-finally
file. In this file, I will add a finally block
that thanks the game player for playing. I will
start this on line 9 with the word, finally, and
a colon. Then, I will make sure I am indented on
the following line and add a print statement to
thank the player for playing. Then, I will run
this code twice. The first time I run it, I will
enter a legitimate value, and we see the try,
else, and finally blocks all ran. Next, I will
run this code and enter an illegitimate value,
and we get the except clause but we also get the
thank you message. In this case, the try, except,
and finally blocks ran. As we get ready to move
to the next piece of exception handling, raises,
know this about the try block. First, it cannot
run by itself. Secondly, a try block must have
an except clause or a finally clause, or the code
will fail. An else clause is not always needed,
though normally, one would want an else clause
to continue running code if the try block does
not cause an exception unless the subsequent code
to run needs to happen after the finally block.
The whole goal with the try, except, else, and
finally blocks is to control error messages as
they happen and allow an app to end gracefully
rather than have a hard crash take place, which,
when occurring too many times, may dissuade people
from wanting to use an app. To summarize exception
handling, this chart helps us understand an
important nuance with . It's essential to
understand the run flow and interactions between
try, except, else, and finally blocks. If an
error is raised within an except, else, or finally
block, this error will not be caught by the same
except block. Rather, it will turn into a runtime
error. Before that happens, if a finally block
exists, the finally block will always execute. For
instance, if there's a runtime error in the except
block, that block will halt at the error. Python
will then look for a finally block. If found,
the finally block will execute, followed
by the raising of the unhandled exception.